Ruth Colvin Papers
Ruth Colvin Papers
circa 1980-2010
Colvin, Ruth J.
2 linear ft.
American literacy advocate and author. Collection includes videotapes, clippings, slides, and presentations and publications by Colvin.
3647885
Biographical History
Ruth Johnson Colvin (1917- ) is an American literacy advocate and author, and the founder of the non-profit organization Literacy Volunteers of America (LVA). Colvin founded LVA in Syracuse, New York in 1962 with the goal of training tutors in reading and English as a Second Language (ESL) to combat illiteracy; although the original focus was the local community, the organization expanded its work across the United States and then internationally. In 2002 the company merged with Laubach Literacy International (LLI). LLI was also founded in Syracuse, in 1955 by Frank C. Laubach, and its philosophy of "Each one teach one" shared LVA's focus on teaching new readers to teach others. The new organization, named ProLiteracy Worldwide, funds or supports literacy efforts of various kinds in all 50 states as well as countries in Asia, Africa, Latin America, and the Middle East. As of 2010 the company had 330 programs in 42 states with over 100,000 volunteers and students
Colvin has received dozens of awards for her work in combating illiteracy. In December of 2006, she was awarded the Presidential Medal of Freedom, the nation's highest civilian honor.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ruth Colvin Papers consists of videotapes, clippings, slides, and presentations and publications by Colvin.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is unprocessed and remains in original order.
Related Material
is also the repository of the
Laubach Literacy International Records
and the
Frank C. Laubach Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Colvin, Ruth J.; Literacy Volunteers of America.; English language -- Study and teaching -- Foreign speakers.; Literacy -- Developing countries.; Literacy -- United States.; New literates, Writing for.; Videotapes.; Audiotapes.; Audiocassettes.; Compact discs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Textbooks.; Teachers.
Access Restrictions
The collection is currently unprocessed and not available for research. Please contact for more information. In addition, the collection is fully restricted until the death of the donor. Until such time, written permission of the donor is required for access to the collection.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ruth Colvin, 2011.
Inventory
- Audiovisual materials
  - 25 Year Recognition of LVA by Channel 5, 17 September 1987; colvin_r_0013; VHS (Box 1)
  - Hour Magazine Ruth Colvin, undated; colvin_r_0018; VHS (Box 1)
  - IESC “1992 Frank Pace Award”, undated; colvin_r_0015; VHS (Box 1)
  - IESC “Frank Pace Award”, 01 April 1992; colvin_r_0014; VHS (Box 1)
  - Improving Lives through Literacy (SSC360 Rewind), undated; colvin_r_0021; DVD (Box 2)
  - In the Beginning was the Word: Teaching Reading and Writing Through the Bible Training Video, undated; colvin_r_0017; VHS (Box 1)
  - India, A Land Of Contrasts, undated; colvin_r_0002; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
  - India - The Spirit Of Sharing, undated; colvin_r_0003; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 1)
  - International Journals, International Slide Presentations, International Reports, undated; colvin_r_0001; CD (Box 2)
  - International Journals, Reports, Scripts of slide presentations, undated; colvin_r_0004; CD (Box 2)
  - Interview with Nancy Duffy; Ruth Colvin / Medal of Excellence, 12 May 1984; colvin_r_0009; 3/4 inch videotape: U-matic SP (Box 1)
  - Literacy Volunteer Award, 30 June 1987; colvin_r_0010; VHS (Box 1)
  - Literacy Volunteers Special - Ruth and Bob Colvin, 27 Feb 1981; colvin_r_0005; VHS (Box 1)
  - National Women’s Hall Of Fame - 1993 Honors Ceremonies, 09 October 1993; colvin_r_0016; VHS (Box 1)
  - Newsmaker - Ruth Colvin, 10 August 1987; colvin_r_0012; VHS (Box 1)
  - Ruth [Colvin] Presentation Award, 30 June 1987; colvin_r_0011; VHS (Box 1)
  - S.U. [Syracuse University] Graduation, 12 May 1984; colvin_r_0007; VHS (Box 1)
  - [Syracuse University] Graduation, 12 May 1984; colvin_r_0008; VHS (Box 1)
  - Video for Mrs. Colvin - South Africa, 1984; colvin_r_0006; 3/4 inch videotape: U-matic SP (Box 1)
  - [untitled], undated; colvin_r_0019; VHS (Box 1)
  - [untitled], undated; colvin_r_0020; 1/8 inch audio cassette (Box 1)